so I thought we could discuss
authenticity as the or lack of
authenticity is the main obstacle
to understanding the
Dum
so first of all like um instead of
describing authenticity in positive
terms can we come up with some way to
describe how lack of authenticity would
be most concretely manifested in people [Music]
there's lying to others of course which
is like even
further into the rabbit hole
authenticity in authenticity sorry in
authenticity yeah so if you lie to
others it will be impossible to stop
lying to yourself which fundamentally is
what authen lack of authenticity is
inauthenticity lying to yourself
like things are a certain way but you
insist in regarding them in another way
because it's more
comfortable [Music]
[Music]
so yeah that would be one one way
um is there something
that let's say somebody who hasn't found
a way of
suffering um is there a way to know that they are
um is there a way to know that they are
not being authentic just based on how
they go through life how they
feel or somebody can ask if they have an
attitude of personal responsibility for
everything they do say think and
feel and that's an attitude that one can
adopt and can
develop and to the extent that one does
not have that sense of full complete
responsibility I would say someone is
inauthentic yeah but how how would it
more accurately like feel not to have
that attitude versus having that
attitude now somebody for example might feel like
now somebody for example might feel like
a victim of
circumstances like the origin of my pain
is coming from outside ex external and
so the problem needs to be
resolved out there in an assum with
external World rather than um on the
level of one's own views and
actions yes so that would be
um I was referring more to like so as a
result of this that you're talking about
now a person would feel a sense of
safety but a sense of false safety yes
because not acknowledging things or not
recognizing the truth of things in the
most General sense like not
recognizing or acknowledging the way
things are not in some mystical sense
but genuinely the State of Affairs let's
say results in a form of ignorance is
bliss as they say uhhuh yes so
practically speaking that's why the the
suas are saying that recognizing Dua can
only result in two things either Noble
search or Madness mhm
bewilderment because recognizing Dua is basically
because recognizing Dua is basically
recognizing or
acknowledging the State of Affairs not
in a external sense but internally like
your liability to lose things that are dear
liability to lose things that are dear
to you your liability to doubt not
knowing what the way out of suffering is
liability to
um uncertainty
to sickness aging and death so these are
things that by not acknowledging them
mhm you would feel a sense
of
relief but it's it's a unfounded belief
so then what I'm getting at is that if a
person doesn't feel a sense
of
um not like not like acute kind of like
you know uh um falling apart sort of
constant anxiety but just a a subtle
sense of unease like something is not
right then it has to be either because they
then it has to be either because they
are in arut or they are covering
something up because you are liable to
sickness aging and
death unless you're narat and so that
has to be recognized it like if you keep
that recognition if you're not covering
it up which is fundamentally like what
authenticity is not covering those
fundamental liabilities up then
well it's going to have to
feel uh there's going to have to be some
degree of dissonance there some degree
of
um uh yeah discomforts so that's that's
one of the ways to
measure uh lack of authenticity like if
you have the sense that everything will
be all right mhm like things would just
turn out you don't have a reason to
believe you don't have a justification
why you believe that it's just like I
just live life as if things are going to be
live life as if things are going to be
all right in the end so that's covering
up that
fundamental Factor recognition that
maybe maybe it's not like that so
perhaps you can find more ways in which
uh in authenticity manifests like for
example if if one finds justification
for certain action or abuse because the
majority things like that right or
because you belong to a certain group or
a society holds certain values like this
um and then um just uncritically taking
that over can be a way of of having that
false sense of Safety and Security by
just doing what everybody else is doing
so
authenticity implies stepping away from
that um which means that you're going to
find yourself more on your own and that
is experiential unpleasant because one's
ignorance or doubt about what is right
what is wrong what are going to be the
consequences of my actions and so on
that's going to be highlighted if you
are not just um casually moving along
with um what an anonymous day or Crow or
H happens to be
doing that that's another way which
doesn't mean that one cannot associate
with other people externally objectively
but we're talking about an inner
attitude of not just doing something
because a certain group or a certain
tradition tells you that that's good to
do um one needs to be more critical than
that and recognizing even
if even if you follow it's not like I
will not not do anything
because in the end you would be trusting
yourself still when you go when you if
you just assume that by not following
anyone uhhuh you already being authentic
that that wouldn't be the case because
you might still be covering up the fact
that you yourself are still liable to
doubt like you're not sure what's what's
right so it's not enough to just dismiss
all authority authorities for example
it's just a fundamental recognition like
no no whether I agree with others or not
I don't know what is correct so I will
be agreeing with something uh it's it's
inevitable but
then the the underlying problem can only
be fixed by recognizing that liability
to doubt not by um finding ways to stop
recognizing it so that it stops hurting
MH and that's why it's um the D goes
against the grain basically because in
order to recognize in order to work
towards fixing a problem you have to
keep it in sight and keeping it in sight
metaphorically speaking in this case is
not going to be pleasant like if you
have a any kind of
illness going through and
life-threatening illness in this case um
which is ignorance like not
understanding the for Noble Truths
should be considered like the worst of
all esses because it is the thing that
subjects you to the to the worst type of
pain of you know rebirth and um sness
aging and death Even In This Very life
so any kind of sickness that you could
get like uh bodily sickness is kind of
secondary to the fundamental sickness of
not knowing the way out of suffering
that's the only way that any um worldly
thing would be able to affect you so
then keeping that in sight it's like you
can either forget that you have terminal
cancer and and
like kind of not even like you you were
told and you decided to forget about it
but like you have a sense that it could
be but you kind of you don't go to the
doctor to ask you just decide to
live the rest of your time whatever
whatever that is in the comfort of just
not having to think about that and
that's what more like what in
authenticity is it's not like you knew
it and then you decided to ignore it
it's more like you have a a vague sense
that there's something there but you're
refusing to acknowledge it it's like
like in a room you might have you know a
dark corner of the room it's not
necessarily in sight but it's there and
like it's the dirt is building up in
that corner MH uh so and you
postpone actually going there and
cleaning it so that's what that's more
what it's like
so all
this uh
external Conformity to tradition and all
that sort of stuff those are just like
the different mechanisms that you could
use to cover up that liability to
uncertainty because if the group says
something and you go along with it well
that provides that kind of
um yeah distraction from having to to
question like well whether or not they
are right is the problem that I am
addressing through
this whatever it might be even the right
problem to focus on in the first place
so you recognize there's so much stuff
to doubt to
question um that in the
end any sort of
um any sort of like
fixed first principle that you start
from could be could be put into question
so that's that can't be something that
you find safety in if you are
recognizing it right it's going to be
it's going to be um at least somewhat
unsettling it has to be mhm
so that's so a desire for let's say
distraction or doing things in order to
feel comfortable by definition means that
comfortable by definition means that
there are things that one wants to
distract oneself from or that there is
an underlying discomfort that one
doesn't want to face so rather than
spending time to organize one's
pleasures and and Comforts like on the
inner let's say emotional or
psychological level not like having a
roof over your head and some close to
right that that's quite necessary right
so we're talking on another on another
level um then um someone who is
authentic would recognize that and turn
around like what is it that I'm right
now not wanting to see through my desire
to be distracted or to dissolve in a
group and things like that and that has
got to become The Habit in if ifone
wants to move towards being authentic
because if there truly wouldn't be
anything if that dis quiet wouldn't be
there then it would not be necessary to
seek sensual Pleasures or to find that
um let's say full sense of safety
because because all of that would be
unnecessary yeah so you can ask yourself
like so if I don't do anything will I
suffer like in the sense of like I just
suspend all my engagements mhm that I
might have accumulated over time
and um I just don't commit to anything
basically will I will that uncertainty
start to show up if it does it's not
because like the uncertainty is a result of you
like the uncertainty is a result of you
not having the engagements anymore it's
that these things were covering up yeah
the Insurgency but often it's seen the
other way around like if I start to
practice restraint or renunciation I am
suffering because I I'm restraining
myself now but it's not like that it's
that was that unpleasantness that comes
when you don't give in that is what was
already there kind of lurking and you
were sweeping it under the rug Yeah by
um distracting yourself with pleasure
yeah so it's not so much a movement
towards something positive say that one
doesn't have right now it's it's a sort
of it's inverted it's like an uncovering
of something which is already there yeah
stop doing certain things most
importantly like through virtue and sens
trains stop doing certain
things so that um what's already there
can become clear
so rather than seeing it more
as I've heard that Sly used before like
you have
um like a glass with water and and it
has mud in it m and you need to stop
shaking it so that you know the the mud
will go to the bottom yeah but that that
would usually be used in the context of
like you know focusing the mind and
concentration techniques but in this
case it is exactly what you're doing but
in terms of your actions like stop
stirring it up through greed div verion
delusion so that it all sinks to the
bottom and you can start um recognizing
that that that dirt where it is um so
and it's that's where you will start to
see what that that those underlying
Tendencies where the mind mind kind of
um in and of itself it just needs or or
has certain certain pressure certain
inclinations that it has to give into
and uh you would only start recognizing
that if you stop feeding them so that's
that is why authenticity is important to
understanding the dhama
because the things that need to be
abandoned and addressed and
overcome are things that
are very easy to ignore or things that
are very easy to overlook so the default
tendency is not to see them like what
GRE divion illusion are they're not
these um objects or
or direct entities in front of you yeah
yeah they're not like direct um
perceptions that you can get like it is
all on that same level of the things
that you're covering
up so that's why
uh lack of authenticity would
essentially make you incapable of
recognizing your own defilements mhm
because you are everything you do is is
already based on them like way down the
line so how can you possibly um like see
the source of the river to put it that
source of the pollution when you're
already uh engaged with like the the
dirt that comes way way past it so
yeah that's why it's um it's not like a
philosophical um concept only it has
very acute significance
to recognizing what craving is because
you can't abandon craving if if you
haven't recognized it to be MH yeah so
people need to recognize that to
actually come to terms with craving it's
going to be unpleasant yeah but can we
make it more explicit why that is so for
example um like like what is the most dear or
um like like what is the most dear or
cherished thing that that is most
difficult to give
up like what is going to be
challenged let's say inwardly for lack
of a better words if if one is coming to
terms with craving or what that is
fueled and maintained by
craving well what I'm trying to get at
is is that it is one's own identity that
that at some points is going to be
challenged by all this um and so perhaps
you could say that Safety and Security
yet it it begins by outter comfort and
distraction and stuff like that but
fundamentally one sort of takes refuge
in on as we sort of said already
somewhat earlier but that needs to go as
well if one wants to gain the true
refuge in terms of Dharma so one's own
identity comes up for uh let's say in
investigation as well if if you remove
like the outer ways that you were covering up
the outer ways that you were covering up
that recognition so it's it's basically
impossible that you'll get to that core
which is your identity if you still have
like if you still maintain the things
that uh that are result of that identity
let's say yeah like the the
censal averse um distracted actions deluded
averse um distracted actions deluded
careless actions MH there's no way that
you will see the source where that
that's coming from which is the identity
if you're still maintaining it so
that's why authenticity is not just a a
choice of like taking up a certain
attitude as um as you would just like
change your mindset or something it's it
is bound with the choices that you make
so like there are certain choices that
you can't make and be fully authentic at
the same time and those are the things
that go against the precepts well the
the things that an narun cannot do most
fundamentally um the the five things
that that cannot do is like killing
stealing lying sexual intercourse and
taking intoxicant any of those things by doing
intoxicant any of those things by doing
them you are being
inauthentic um to a varing degree of
course but fundamentally if you if you
training yourself um those things need to go for
yourself um those things need to go for
you to uncover start
uncovering um the stuff that you cover
up by doing
them
and now if someone has been following
this so far um and a sense of anxiety
begins to
arise then
what well you you want
to also question that like you can't um
assume that just because you're feeling
anxiety is necessarily correct so what
is the anxiety that I am or what is the
basis for me experiencing this anxiety
MH um it has to be based
on recognition of things that you're
genuinely liable too like you don't
fabricate that sense of anxiety to kind
of give yourself a a boost of of of
sense of urgency in the practice it has
to be something that is already there
you're not like creating it m so you
recognize the things that that already
are lurking there in your experience
like um your own body you don't know
uh you you you you have no access to its
to its to the like gears and in the
mechanism that that's that keep it
working your basic organs function
basally so then so then um you realize
on that level like that
anxiety is the anxiety is in things
being a certain way like the anxiety is
not something you fabricate and so the
practice then is once a person starts to
to feel that
anxiety um on that in that right way
then the practice is not to like fix the
anxiety or resolve it it's to go through
it so to say so that that anxiety ceases
to cause you suffering MH because as
theha said um the like uh impermanence
andury um suffering and not self these
are the characteristics of the agates
it's not like or your entire experience
it's not like things are that way only
when you're ignorant so so the the fact
of the Aggregates being suffering being
um
unsatisfactory would
remain always like even even when you're
not ignorant anymore these things are
still an anxious mhm but you are not
subject to anxiety anymore because
you're not invested
anymore yeah that's
right so that's how that's that uh kind
of a perpendicular Direction instead of
like doing something to the anxiety or
or covering it up or managing it you
find a way so
that it's it just doesn't it just doesn't
it's it just doesn't it just doesn't
affect you so it's um I came up with an
analogy it's like you have a bucket or
or a barrel that that's going to be
filled with
liquid the solution to freedom from
suffering is not to limit the amount of
liquid that's going to come in or the
types of liquid that are going to come
in it's to make it so that the barrel
has no
bottom so that basically there is no
type of anxiety that would be capable of
overwhelming your mind not like the
anxiety is limited now and that's why I
don't get overwhelmed it's you want to
go in the direction of making yourself
immovable to any amount of of anxiety
let alone
like you have to overcome not just um
physical pain and and uh things that can
come from other people it's your own
mind fundamentally yes that has these
these susceptibility to these emotions
and states and that would that's what
you have to
overcome um so yeah so this anxiety is
related to a sense of ground L to to the
point that one has not understood that
there there will be anxiety yeah or
rather one will be affected by anxiety
that you're suffering yeah so then
anxiety that's not resisted or anxiety
that's that's properly understood is not
suffering that's why it's like it's it
it feels it might feel pessimistic MH
when you have wrong view yeah but when
when you understand then it's just the
way things are it's just realist and
then you can have the right type of joy
and the right type of uh peace in the
face of anxiety not not at the expense
of it m and here you should perhaps also
emphasize that you know for some people
this anxiety might border on let's say
depression and depression is can be in
general terms characterized as the Mind
begins to sink and you don't know how to
climb out of that basically so The
Virtue and the Sens restraint in this
case provide sort of a scaffolding for
you to hold on to that it doesn't become
too much so on the one hand we could say
that perhaps this anxiety is never going
to fully reveal itself without having
the virtue and the sensory straight in
place be beforehand so on one level
there is sort of a buffer like if one
doesn't restrain oneself this is never
going to happen but one can get sort of
caught in this intermediate space and
then the the way to not be overwhelmed
is in fact to attend more closely to
one's virtue and one's sense restraints
if one doesn't want to practically
become overwhelmed by the anxiety that's
going to arise if one moves into the
let's say genuine authenticity
here can we say that like virtu sense
restraint kind of make
one face this anxiety but like
progressively with like the right type
of basis instead of like just being
confronted like to the full extent of it
like at the moment of death or when one
like start to lose his senses to get
very sick but never trying will be
fun yeah because the minds because if
it's done rightly it will be a training
of the mind and to the extent that the
mind is strange it will be capable of
enduring basically things that you now
take for granted falling apart yeah it's
it's it's um basically if a person who
hasn't developed virtue is a person who
by default cannot put up with that uh
uncertainty that would be associated
with death for example like they need to
try to outrun it in some case and when
they're still healthy that attempt to
outrun the anxiety the natural
uncertainty of the Aggregates manifest
through these actions of sensuality and
and and all that but then when death
comes and there you can't even move
anymore uh then like all of that stuff
that you would be kind of letting out
into the world you can't anymore so so
it's all kind of contained and the the
pressure and starts boiling yeah so
that's where um that's why it's
important because then that makes it so
that virtu and sens Trin makes it so
that no matter how much of that
internal uh discomfort and and and
pressure you come up with it won't go
past your actions your responses to it
won't go past a certain point and that
in end of itself makes it bother you
less not because like you got rid of it
but because you are less invested or
less identified with that pressure just
to the extent that you are now able to
not do things on account of it's the
it's really that need to respond to the
anxiety in some way or another that
makes you liable to it because that's
that's the craving yeah the craving is
not like the presence of this it's the
fact that you need to do something about
it mhm yeah feel that you need to do
something about it yeah yeah the
interesting thing is there are actually
quite a few discourses where somebody
where some Monk is like greatly ill and
basically on his death bed and then
somebody calls the Buddha and say out of
compassion have a talk with his Monk and
uh quite frequently that monk actually
attains one of the stages on account of
having a conversation with the Buddha
but why is that so because he's already
no no longer interested in sanal
Pleasures because he is about to die
he's just lying there basically so the
so the usual Comforts and the escapes
that's all cut off that is the whole
significance of that has ceased but
against an understanding that there is
rebirth and all the rest of it it's
still meaningful to attend rightly to
what the Buddha is saying and so on that
in that situation it clicks but this
doesn't mean that one should wait until
one is lying on one's death and and and
feeling miserable but but rather that by
the Contex should be understood like why
did it click for that um let's say
newcomer who was just a biku for a few
few months and he already um became so
tap there on account of listening to the
Buddha because he found himself in
situations where basically the usual
Avenues of distraction and comfort were
just no longer there anymore so he was
forced to be authentic in other words
yeah so he was forced to be authentic um
but it would now be very inauthentic to
start waiting for that situation to
happen yeah because as we were saying
before the virtue I mean obviously that
that as you said that person was a monk
that that's what that would have been
happening in the sutas so if a person
didn't take that first step of of like
serious um dedication to Virtue and
sensor restraint then by that time when
these things come the mind is just going
to be reacting so strongly to that
confinement to like as I was saying
before like the room you was you left
that corner in the room um accumulate
dirt for 50 60 years MH and you think
that in one evening now you're going to
clean it up yeah so um through virtual
and sens restrain you would you would
force like you would make it so that um
the anxiety would be certainly still
unpleasant but uh not to the point where
it would overwhelm you and make you
incapable of contemplating things
rightly because like if if it's
if that has been built up for so
long there's very little very little
chance that you could overcome it um
just in a short period of time
basically and and also the attempt to
overcome it is going to be super
affected with craving because now it's
like you're really trying to just run
away from from the problem like you
don't you don't have that um perspective
now it's like it's it's now like a knee-
your uh impulsive reaction to how do I solve
uh impulsive reaction to how do I solve
this as quickly as possible because now
it's in front of me but uh yeah that
that's the you won't you won't be able to do it
the you won't you won't be able to do it
in like a balanced no uh sort of
reflexive um detached manner MH as you
would when you're still
healthy relatively at
least so that's why you you shouldn't
wait until you're you're old or you're
or you're sick or you're near near death
yeah so to be yeah sorry so how is one
GNA bring death then let's say in the
present because someone might hold the
view that death is a one-time event at
the end of life right that's that's
that's probably the most common view but
you see as long as somebody keeps death
at arms length basically like oh it's
not here it's going to happen to me
later on 10 years 20 years and so on on
account of holding that view one
deprives oneself of understanding what
that is because you because it's
unpleasant to yeah because you yourself
keep ping it in the in in the future so
so if rightly contemplating death is
going to be um useful in the context of
establishing authenticity then then how
can people start thinking rightly about
death now when when the body is still
healthy seems to me that it is worth
well discussing that yeah as we
mentioned before it's authenticity is
like recognizing your diability to death
is is one of the most acute ways
of becoming authen basically so so what
is death Here and
Now would it be like just recollecting
like if I
am attached to some things or some
people and just recognizing that I'm
going to lose them anyway like whatever
I'm doing and just trying to stay with
that pressure that one is feeling on
account of losing
something would it be
describing or describing what death is
what like what one how one could like
recollect this correctly
mhm because there like this is just
like we just lose like everything that
we know and everything that we are
attached to so it's like just
recollecting this trying to see if
like actually I'm attach to something
and this attachment make me suffer if I
lose that things because anyway I'm
going to lose it
so yeah so you are saying it's it's
already guaranteed that whatever you're
holding on to is going to be taken away
from you yeah it's just a question of
time basically so then are you saying that
basically so then are you saying that
one comes closer to death by making an
effort to ask if this would be taken
away from me if that would be taken away
from me is my mind going to be affected
and disturbed by that yes or no and if
you can be without those things good but
know at some point it will come closer
it might start with external things my
house my car then maybe people family
children but in the end it needs to come
closer still um body senses
um memory and so on that is where um
well that is where the real anxiety
begins to arise because that's the very
Foundation of one's experience but now
you're saying that Barrel shouldn't have
a button so what are you taking as a
foundation of your experience at some
point it needs to come to that but
that's probably not really going to land
if if one is still fully attached to all
this external things so so so there is
sort of a movement there and then um
this shouldn't become an INT ual game or
something that you occasionally do this
has to become the backdrop like am I
living my life right now in such a way
that I'm not building up any new
attachments and can I come to terms with
things that I unfortunately have already
become attached to so that's so that's
sort of two tracks and uh that are there
simultaneously and then the question is
well I better not start building up new
attachment because that's moving in the
wrong direction and there is still um
already accumulated material that is not
in my welfare as long as I keep holding
on to it not because in of itself it's
bad but as you just said like it's going
to be taken away from you anyway and
that and that's got to be the starting
point and as long as you haven't given
it up when death comes to claim it well
that's the contradiction right there you
you will be arguing you essentially you
will have a a debate with death and you
can't win no there's no there's no bar
gaining with death that's it then so
then um yeah so that's why virtue and
sensor strange like again it's it's um
you won't be able to see how you depend
on your body or your feelings and and
stuff if you still depend on external
things it's just the the the i in fact
the body when when people are projected
into these externals that's exactly why
they end up conceiving the body as
another kind of external thing like like
uh just the outside shell of um you know
ations or or things that I can directly
perceive not realizing that the body is
actually much more fundamental than that
so you would actually have to withdraw
yourself from these things to to
recognize what that more
fundamental uh dependence is which would
uh
ultimately uh make death be
uncomfortable because if if you're not
holding on to any of these things again
not as a matter of choice but as a
matter of uh having understood that
anxiety and having understood how it's
there on its own uh you didn't create it
it's you basically like having
gratuitous assumptions of moving away
from it then then that if you have that
understanding then you would be unmoved
by by that anxiety so but it all starts
with that because virtue and sensor
chain on the right level taken on the
right level is not just the adherence to
external Behavior as we' said before it
has to be done with that recognition of
like through these actions through this
this abstinence from these actions I am
wearing away my dependence on things
that are not in my control so you need
to keep that connection as the context
to your virtue not like I just do these
these practices and
behaviors it has to be that and then
then you would start to see as well uh
the wrong motivations for keeping the
virtue if those things start to come up
well those would be other
dependences as well as we discussed
before in
the the talk about virtue and
observances so that would be another way
of uh being an authentic like doing the
the observances because even not
necessarily is for the um adherence to
an external tradition but just
automatically just doing it without that
context of uh you know your liability to
suffering and how this is related to
that would make it automatically just be
uh just habits that you're just uh
following for no particular reasons so
yeah that is the Sasa so that is the WR
grasp of habits and virtues and duties
so they might come with let's say some
reward or externally that might things
even U they might make things externally
more comfortable even and one can just
fall asleep in a little corner In Your
cie somewhere entirely Miss the point
yeah um yeah so The Virtue would only
prepare you for death if it's taken in
that on that right level with the
recognition of of how through this this
these things that would make
death um painful I may not be entirely
ering them obviously because there's
more than just virtue but I am for sure
wearing it away like to some degree that
has to be the the recognition that you
do practice virtue with so the less
death can take away from you basically
the less you suffer when death comes
yeah and uh as you said before that's
another thing to to point out like it's
very um it is a very good test to
um it is a very good test to
see like what are
you what what really is your the extent
of your commitment to the practice to
ask yourself yeah sure we all start with
yourself yeah sure we all start with
with attachments that we already have
mhm but is your practice are like are
you still actively accumulating new
attachments in spite of you of you
saying that you're trying to to be free
from suffering so somebody who is who is
says they're practicing the dhama to be
free from suffering but at the same time
is allowing themselves to build up new
attachment that they didn't have before
that's already like that has to be done
because they're covering up
again the inauthenticity they're
covering up how these things are
basically perpetuating and proliferating
the same problem that they're trying to
be free from MH so and and it's often
that's the thing with inauthenticity
it's not um it's a form of ignorance
basically and it's um with all types of
ignorance it's there because you you're
not aware of it like it's not that
people choose to be inauthentic in the
same way that people don't choose to be
ignorant it's just it has to be done
with a certain degree of um negligence
yeah with with not not well that's what
uh
negligence and heed heedfulness is
essentially it's like um
recognizing the things that you're
already liable to and how your actions
are making it worse or making it better
yeah and so also as we said before like
if someone feels the need to um let's
say defend their
views or defend their practices when
questioned or challenged or they fall in
love with their teacher or some or they
cannot leave their Monastery because
that's the only place where I can
practice all of these
are um indications that you are
basically building up new attachment and
that you that you're having the whole
thing backwards that should that should
be a red flag there
but it seems to me that like for a
complete newcomer to just spend some
time alone and inwardly not see yourself
as part of a group and then take on some
virt and sensor train that is how I
think practically all of this starts
yeah right and and also and even
thinking about death even if it is not
that intense it doesn't go that far that
will already p you out of the crowd for
the simple reason that no one else can
die for you right you have to face your
death alone so however much you want to
lose yourself in an anonymous day
thinking about death rightly will bring
the whole thing back to you which is
unpleasant but it can't be otherwise and
and the person should also realize when
that like if there is anything in the
world that could bother you or could uh
um take away your
peace that is what the dhma is supposed
to address because that's something that
can be easily overlooked by just not
thinking about it so then people would
fall into the idea that the D is about
getting special experiences and and uh
special like uh mystical insights and stuff but
like uh mystical insights and stuff but
how many people actually ask themselves
okay but in spite of all this are there
still things that if they happen to me
or if they're taken away from me I could
still suffer if yes then regardless of
all this other stuff I can't tell myself
if I'm being authentic that this is what
the Dum is about MH so it's not like
like it's it's wrong on some kind of um
specific doctrinal grounds to be to be
getting these experiences like because
it doesn't fit with the suta such and
such it's because like if you know that
this is not addressing your liability to
anything it it it can be like the most
um kind of
distant uh unrealistic scenario but
there if there is anything that you feel
could undermine you if it happens MH
that is what the dhama should be about
so then when a person starts to feel
that uh yeah that anxi or uncover really
that anxiety that we mentioned um
whether it's very strong or not you have to ask
it's very strong or not you have to ask
yourself this is or tell yourself this
is what the practice is about so I might
not be able to take it on fully like you
might kind of look at that corner uh
that dirty corner and it might feel
overwhelming so it's not like you have
to take it all at once but you certainly
shouldn't lose the recognition that I I
am not free I am not practicing or I
have not successfully practiced the
Buddhist teaching until that thing
cannot be there even if I want to not
because I stopped acknowledging that
anxiety but like I I
fully uh commit myself to try to bring
it up and it it just can't happen MH but
most people it's just like because
you're not aware of it you naturally
just don't look in that direction and
you can spend your whole life um
building certain you know coping
mechanisms and strategies again without
even noticing that allow you not to
think about that because it's just too
and ironically a lot of what is nowadays
being taught as
meditation helps with not looking at
that dark corner yeah just focus over
here so that you don't need to be there
basically and and the thing is as well
one of the red flags as as related to
what we just mentioned is that it
immediately just gives you
pleasure so it's like right from the
start you there was no no um
like accumulation of dirt from all this
infinite endless onada it was just you
got the pleasure right away you didn't
have to toil through the cleaning up the
the the the crap that was there it just
very quickly you got the pleasure so
that's a red flag because if like these
these um going against like you've been
going with the drain so hard mhm and so
long yeah and so long that going in the
opposite Direction cannot be easy not
that it's impossible but you should be
skeptical of anything that just just
feel easy because yeah that's where the
effort is should see yeah yeah it's not
in yeah the effort is not in um trying
to like gain like committing yourself to
to a meditation technique doing it so
hard 247 it's about uncovering these things
247 it's about uncovering these things
uncovering them and then getting to the
point where you can
face them without fear mhm essentially
so you're not building something really
it's more like you are taking stuff
away until there's nothing left
so uh no coverups left we don't that
kind of assumption often people when they
of assumption often people when they
sign up for such Retreat and and uh
thought the assumption is that I can
regain some control you know because my
world appears to be kind of in chaos I
cannot control you know things bother me
basically I need to go for meditation to
regain kind of control so that's why
it's so kind of appealing in a way yeah
and ironically you would be more closely
seeing or becoming authentic by seeing
wait no I am liable for things to go out
of my control but then that's that's the
solution nobody wants to hear like if
you have if you have like I don't know
you have a leak in your
house and and there's like I don't know
uh you see these these little marks of
water on the roof you don't want to hear
that you have to replace the whole
plumbing system you like you know
tot you don't want to be told that you
have to remove the entire foundation of
the house uh so yes you will you will
like contractor who says oh yeah just
painting is needed it will be fine
exactly exactly but then it's your own
loss because um like it is
like you might live your whole life
um like there's basically a degree where
these things can genuinely seem to stay
with you until the day you die like work
these management methods cover up
methods but at the very least at that
moment moment it it's going to have to
stop working because that's
where your aggregate simply won't listen
to you anymore um all of that stuff that
that you were covering up it will force
itself to the surface like you can't at
that moment you can't um just focus on
Sensations because your senses might be
breaking apart so what Sensations are
you you going to focus on um yeah and
but then you see then then the thing is
if one brings death from um let's say
the future to the present what one will
have to recognize is that actually
that's already the case right now yeah
so it's so it's not like oh I'll just
live my life and then I just hope I have
a peaceful death by which people mean
like you know get a shot of morphine or
you die in your sleep hoping to avoid
the unpleasant sensation but with death
as such they're not concerned yeah
whereas actually death reflected
properly reveals you how as you said
things already are namely agates are
fundamentally already doing their own
thing yeah it it's uh it would be yeah
it's an unfortunate misconception to
think that death is like these uh I
don't know intense bodily pains or
something and then that event those
Sensations or those those things are
going to come at that moment uhuh like
but really death is just um like the
final confirmation of the fact that
these Aggregates are not yours MH it's
just uh so that recognition is like
death is buried into or or underlying
every your experience now because the
ARs are already not in your control so
it's it's you have a
certain it's like you're a dead man
walking essentially like you can walk
but that doesn't mean that you can ever
escape your liability you can do stuff
on top of your liability but not to act
actually change it and that's what uh
like anata means it doesn't mean that
you don't have control in any way like
you're just a robot who who is like
determinist deterministically bound to
make certain make certain actions it
means that whatever action you choose to
do there is that Foundation that
undermines it always so you can't just
like you can't assume yourself to be the
master it's not that um
like that's bad enough for for it to not
be worth taking itself you can only take
it itself if you know that it will go
your way but if there's even a little
chance that somebody else is going to
come like I don't know you're building
you're building a house but
then somebody tells you yeah you're
you're building it but there is a chance
that at any point in time somebody's
going to come and you're going to have
to give it over to them and you're going
to have to leave
mhm you're not going to if you keep that
recognition in your mind it would be
impossible for you to start treating it
internally like no this is my house so
that's what AATA is is about and that's
why all all these things would only be
realized again through authenticity
because it's all in that direction of
lack of control that that's experienced
as initially as as um unpleasant and
unsettling because not again not in
itself but because you have the
need through habitual engagement to
control it so it's like a momentum that
is that is kept going and then you
suddenly put in stop to it and it's like
it wants to keep yeah keep going so
that's why that's the discrepancy that
that you feel um and that's and that's
where the endurance begins like the
moment you hit the
break you better have a seat belt or
else you just lying through the window
or it's or it's like the the the dog the
S of the the wild animals compared to
the senses it's like only when you
actually pin them down finally just stop
running with them that's when you start
feeling the pull yeah and um yeah it can
it's everything just uh there's
sensuality there's uh the core stuff but
even if if you don't really experience
those things like when you're old for
example you might not have that uh intense
you might not have that uh intense
course sensal desire that you had when
you were young but that doesn't mean
that you're free you still have
fundamentally that need for things to go
your way on to some degree like if
there's anything that can upset you
anything that can um that can disturb
your peace that means you haven't come
to
terms with that fundamental uncertainty
of your ear experience